YANYUAN QIAO

yanyuan.qiao@adelaide.edu.au · in Qiao

PRoom 2.05.01, AIML Building, The University of Adelaide, SA 5005, Australia

BIO

Yanyuan Qiao is a Postdoctoral Research Fellow working with A.P. Qi Wu, at the Australian Institute for Machine Learning (AIML), The University of Adelaide. She has been working on multi-modal learning tasks, such as Vision-and-Language Navigation, Text-to-Image Synthesis, and Visual Question Answering, and has published papers in top journals and conferences.

RESEARCH INTEREST

Vision-and-Language, Embodied AI.

EDUCATION

The University of Adelaide, Adelaide, Australia

2020 - 2023

PhD in Computer Science

University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China

2016 - 2019

MEng in Electronics and Communication Engineering

Southeast University, Nanjing, China

2012 - 2016

BEng in Sensor Network Technology

PUBLICATIONS

Journals:

- Yanyuan Qiao, Yuankai Qi, Yicong Hong, Zheng Yu, Peng Wang, Qi Wu, HOP+: History-enhanced and Order-aware Pre-training for Vision-and-Language Navigation, IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI), 2023. (Core rank: A^*)
- Yanyuan Qiao, Chaorui Deng, Qi Wu, Referring Expression Comprehension: A Survey of Methods and Datasets, IEEE Transactions on Multimedia (TMM), 2020. (Core rank: A^*)
- Zhiwei Fang, Jing Liu, Yong Li, **Yanyuan Qiao**, Hanqing Lu, Improving Visual Question Answering Using Dropout and Enhanced Question Encoder, Pattern Recognition (PR), 2019. (Core rank: *A**)

Conferences:

- Yanyuan Qiao, Yuankai Qi, Zheng Yu, Jing Liu, Qi Wu, March in Chat: Interactive Prompting for Remote Embodied Referring Expression, ICCV, 2023. (Core rank: *A**)
- Yanyuan Qiao, Zheng Yu, Qi Wu, VLN-PETL: Parameter-Efficient Transfer Learning for Vision-and-Language Navigation, ICCV, 2023. (Core rank: A^*)
- Yanyuan Qiao, Yuankai Qi, Yicong Hong, Zheng Yu, Peng Wang, Qi Wu, HOP: History-and-Order Aware Pre-training for Vision-and-Language Navigation, CVPR, 2022. (Core rank: A^*)
- Yanyuan Qiao, Qi Chen, Chaorui Deng, Ning Ding, Yuankai Qi, Mingkui Tan, Xincheng Ren, Qi Wu, R-GAN: Exploring Human-like Way for Reasonable Text-to-Image Synthesis via Generative Adversarial Networks, ACM MM, 2021. (Core rank: *A**)
- Yanyuan Qiao, Zheng Yu, Jing Liu, RANKVQA: Answer Re-ranking for Visual Question Answering, ICME, 2020. (Core rank: *A*) (Oral)
- Yanyuan Qiao, Zheng Yu, Jing Liu, VC-VQA: Visual calibration mechanism for Visual Question Answering, ICIP, 2020. (Core rank: *B*)
- Zhiwei Fang, Jing Liu, Yanyuan Qiao, Qu Tang, Yong Li, Hanqing Lu, Enhancing Visual Question Answering Using Dropout, ACM MM, 2018. (Core rank: A*)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Vision-and-Language Navigation

May 2021 - present

- Proposing a novel paradigm that applies LLMs to generate step-by-step instructions to guide the agent navigate for remote embodied referring expression task.
- Exploring parameter-efficient transfer learning methods for VLN and proposing VLN-PETL specifically designed for VLN tasks.
- Proposing a history-enhanced and order-aware pre-training and the complementing fine-tuning paradigm with an external memory network for VLN tasks.

Text-to-Image Synthesis

Sept 2020 - Apr 2021

 Proposing a novel Generative Adversarial Network to produce photo-realistic and reasonable images from the corresponding intricate descriptions by imitating the drawing process of humans.

Visual Question Answering

Sept 2017 - Feb 2020

- Developing a visual calibration mechanism for VQA systems with a visual feature reconstruction module that can guide predicted answers to be more relevant to the image content.
- Proposing a new VQA paradigm to achieve a better understanding of visual information and overcome the language-bias problem.
- Proposing a siamese dropout mechanism to enhance the robustness of the VQA model.

Honors and Awards

Honors & Scholarship:

• Ecoles d'été France Excellence Scholarship (¥15,000)	2018
 University of Chinese Academy of Sciences 2016-2017 Outstanding Student 	2017
 University of Chinese Academy of Sciences Academic Scholarship 	2016
Southeast University 2014-2015 Course Scholarship	2015
 Southeast University Individual Scholarship for Excellence in Social Practice 	2013
 Southeast University Individual Scholarship for Excellence in Volunteer Service 	2013
Awards & Prizes:	

• 4th place in the VQA Challenge at CVPR Workshop 2018

2018

TECHNICAL AND PERSONAL SKILLS

- Programming Languages: Python, C++, Matlab, LaTeX.
- Libraries: PyTorch, Numpy, Caffe.
- Platforms: Linux, Windows.
- Languages: English (Fluent), Mandarin (Native).

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- Conference Reviews: ACM MM 2020/2021, BMVC 2021/2023, CVPR 2021/2022, NeuIPS 2023.
- Journal Reviews: IJCV, TIP, TMM, TOMM